[Music]
so the conversation between Brett
Weinstein and Richard Dawkins has just
come out they have it in October and a
lot of people were really looking
forward to it and thinking it could be a
really significant moment in
evolutionary biology I know that's how
Brett was thinking about it and by
coincidence I've just come back from
doing a whole set of interviews with
Brett and with Heather and one of the
things we talked about was the Dawkins
debate so in a minute I'm gonna play the
whole of that interview with Brett but I
just wanted to frame it first because I
know for Brett in particular the point
of difference the disagreement that they
had is something he thinks has held up
evolution since about the 1970s my
argument would be Dawkins self-esteem
was a triumph it really would have a
hard time having been better from the
point of view of the amount of
contribution in one small volume but it
did uh sure in a broken assumption that
because we never fixed it has become the
obstacle that I think my entire
generation now faces in the study of
human evolution at least and it's about
time we fixed it and I thought this
little interaction right at the
beginning of the debate said a lot about
the different perspectives that Brett
and Richard Dawkins are taking into it
I'm gonna play it quickly now The
Selfish Gene you wrote in 1976 am I
correct about that you were 35 years old
so Richard wrote that book as a young
gun and I find it shocking that I have
to say this but I think that that book
is still cutting-edge and so one of the
things we may end up talking about
tonight is why it is that there has not
been more progress after the huge burst
of activity that we saw in the late 60s
and early 70s why my era has been much
quieter with respect to important
discoveries about evolution that we all
agree are true you have anything to add
yes I I don't quite know why you find it
knocking I mean of course we all pay lip
service to the idea that progress is
good and we should be changing all the
time but what if we're right and so it
does it doesn't necessarily follow that
that what people thought in the nineteen
sixties and seventies is still largely
believed is a bad thing maybe it is
actually right so I'm going to play the
whole interview with Brett now but why I
think this is really important is that
this goes really to the heart of a lot
of the key questions particularly the
utility of religion therefore the new
atheist framework that Dawkins is coming
from I'm going to let Brett examine it
explore it and describe in his own words
and play the whole interview now
recently you had a very high profile
conversation with Richard Dawkins in
Chicago how did it go I think it went
very well
it's a conversation I had been waiting
to have literally for decades in
particular I've been very interested to
know what he would respond if a careful
articulation of the idea that religion
has to be an adaptation that we should
view the religious beliefs of
populations that have held beliefs for
thousands of years we should look at the
more or less as we look at an eye or a
wing or any other phenomenon that has
the hallmarks of adaptation rather than
looking at them as a mind virus the way
Dawkins has famously dismissed them it
has always seemed to me that if the
proper argument was laid in front of him
that Dawkins being a famously honest
broker as an intellectual would have to
acknowledge some reality to it and I
think we got closer to that than many
people imagined would be possible it was
clear on stage that Dawkins was in
tension with himself over his his
beliefs and on the one hand when I
pointed out that mind virus suggests
that
these belief systems are pathological to
the people who hold them and that that
is not only on unproductive way to
approach people but that it is at odds
with the elegance of the way selection
tends to work he initially argued that
people had over interpreted the question
of mind virus and that really every gene
in the genome could be portrayed in such
a light which is an argument I certainly
understand it's not the connotation
people get when you say mind virus I him
and I said that the connotations when
you say mind virus are that these people
are mentally ill and he protested he
said well they are mentally ill so you
know on the one hand he was being you
know the careful dawkins that we
remember from you know the mid-seventies
and on the other hand he was being the
strident older dawkins that gets himself
into such trouble over religion and both
things were evident within you know a
couple of sentences of each other
because this this question is right at
the heart of New Atheism effectively on
stage I told Dawkins that religion
cannot be a mind virus on stage I told
Dawkins that religions that have existed
for thousands of years cannot be mind
viruses but that New Atheism can and I
really believe this new atheism is novel
it has not stood the test of time and in
fact it creates a problem for many of us
who might otherwise be willing to be
called atheists because it has taken on
an ideological fervor rather than being
a an argument that there is no
supernatural explanation for the
phenomena that we find within the
universe it has become a a challenge to
people who view the universe otherwise
and that desire to challenge people
rather than
Challenge ideas is not helpful even if
New Atheism began in a productive
direction it became so focused in doing
battle on behalf of an idea that I think
it just lost its way and it ceased to be
able to see that it had gone too far
that in fact it is one thing to point
out that religious traditions are not
literal it is another thing to argue
that they are error because that's not
what they are there they are much more
than error what's your definition of the
moment I've heard you say before that
they are metaphorically true but
literally literally false my argument
has been that religions are compendiums
of a kind of wisdom but that that wisdom
is non literal so that when we evaluate
the content of let's say a biblical text
we if we look at it with respect to did
these events occur then we will dismiss
it if we say what would the effect on an
individual be of believing that these
events had occurred the effect would be
positive from the point of view of their
genetic fitness that is to say how well
they are able to serve their genetic
interests would be enhanced by believing
in these structures so for example if
one behaves in life in such a way as to
make it more likely that one will go to
heaven and make it less likely that one
will end up in hell it just so happens
that behaving in that honorable way will
cause your descendants to be well
positioned in society to be well thought
of to be treated well whereas if you
betray people and act like a jerk it's
very likely that your descendants will
experience a cost for your
untrustworthiness so it is no accident I
am arguing that behaving so is to get
you into heaven does not actually get
you into a place called heaven but it
does get you into an analogous place in
which your descendants are better off
after your death their life is better
after your death it's a kind of life
after death but it's not literal so guys
like Dawkins are unable to see this kind
of value that is to say a pragmatic
value of these belief systems because
they are too caught up in evaluating the
claims that are tied up in in these
texts so in effect they're missing the
forest for the trees because the
falseness of the literal claim obscures
the value of belief in that claim what
effect has that had on evolutionary
biology for example evolutionary biology
has been stuck in my opinion it has been
stuck since about 1976 which is the year
that Dawkins published The Selfish Gene
as a 35 year old young gun the reason
that has been stuck especially with
respect to understanding human beings is
that although Dawkins
made a quantum leap in that book in the
direction of a proper theory of human
evolution
he also made an error that has gone
unrepaired in the entire intervening
period when he introduced the concept of
memes thereby providing a mechanism for
discussing cultural evolution in
rigorous terms by analogy to genes
he argued that memes evolve as if in a
new primeval soup he uses that phrase
and were that the case it basically
suggests an independence of memetic
products and the genetic underpinnings
of our physical nature if those two
things are independent then you could
get things like religions that evolved
to further their own interests at the
expense of the creatures on whose minds
they are running that would make sense
given his his argument
if it is not correct that memes exist in
a new primeval soup then it is likely
and I argued on stage that in fact
cultural traits are obligated to serve
genetic interests so in such a context a
religion as mind virus makes no sense
because what we can infer is that as
much as people may believe things that
are literally false they are believing
them for reasons that are apparently in
the interests of their genomes and that
is where a proper theory of human
evolution would have to go so in essence
tied up in this one very small error is
the entire branch of the tree that we
should be exploring in order to
understand ourselves as products of
adaptive evolution and more often than
not in complex systems when we get stuck
it is it is something of this nature
where the tiniest alteration of an
assumption has giant cascading effects
and very frequently because of the way
we pass on the tradition of studying
these things one generation creates an
assumption that isn't quite right it
hands it off to the next generation who
doesn't even realize that it's making an
assumption at all it takes on that
assumption so early and you know the
graduate study that nobody thinks to
question it and by the time that
generation matures into to teaching
their own intellectual descendants it
just has become part of the landscape
therefore the solution to fixing stuck
fields very frequently involves doing
exactly the opposite of what the
mythology of science suggests fallacy of
science suggests you're sort of moving
out on the frontier looking farther but
when you're stuck looking out on the
frontier you may be on a artificially
short branch you know looking for leaves
where there aren't any when you what you
really need to do is go down the trunk
of the tree and find the branching point
the place where you lost track of the
argument and then follow another branch
up so going down
the broken assumption and then traveling
up another branch is the key to success
and my argument would be Dakin 'less
Selfish Gene was a triumph it really
would have a hard time having been
better from the point of view of the
amount of contribution in one small
volume but it did uh sure in a broken
assumption that because we never fixed
it has become the obstacle that I think
my entire generation now faces in the
study of human evolution at least and
it's about time we fixed it and if we
did fix it what would the effect be well
the effect would be spectacular and I
think quite jarring to many people
because what we tend to think when we
think about ourselves as products of
evolution is that somehow we have
stepped off the end of the evolutionary
tape that we are Pleistocene
hunter-gatherers living in modern world
it doesn't look anything like the
savannahs of Africa but that's not in
fact the case the fact is evolution has
been with us every step of the way and
while we are not adapted to the modern
world there's not been enough time with
social media for example for us to have
traditions that make any sense in that
context that is not true for things that
are several hundred years old so were we
to understand just how much our culture
and tradition has been serving our
genomes we would a start to recognize
that the study of evolution is much more
central to understanding ourselves than
we have given it credit for and B this
is the part I'm really hoping we can get
to very quickly be we would realize that
we are programmed we are culturally
programmed for something that cannot be
defended something we must resist and
that's a very jarring discovery but from
my perspective the clock is ticking
we need to figure that out very quickly
so that we can get on to reauthorize
towards objectives that actually match
the values we think we hold our
conscious minds need to reauthorize
purpose so that we can not simply be the
the the slaves of an evolutionary
purpose that is not honorable and will
lead to our extinction can you make that
a bit more explicit what is that genetic
program our genetic program is very
simple it has given us the identical
purpose of every other evolved creature
and that identical purpose involves
spreading our genetic Spelling's people
who believe in evolution will all
resonate with that what we don't
typically say is that our genomes will
spread our particular Spelling's to the
exclusion of other spellings even when
the other Spelling's are better so if
for example I have a gene for a
particular respiratory enzyme and
someone else has a gene that's 20% more
efficient well that gene is better but
my respiratory gene will seek to
displace to drive to extinction that
superior gene so that it may spread that
should give us a clue that something
about this landscape is not simply about
progress it is about progress in a very
narrow sense that is quite dangerous in
the larger case individuals will advance
their own genetic spellings by
displacing individuals that are less
likely to have them that is to say
murder genocide warfare these are all
evolutionary processes and we are wired
to deploy them when we detect certain
features of the landscape and so
we exist at this strange nexus we are
the most remarkable structures in the
known universe the computing power that
we have between our ears and more
importantly the computing power that we
can muster when we team up is absolutely
immense and we are capable of
breathtaking feats of insight and beauty
but all of these things evolved for this
simple mind-numbing purpose that is no
different from the purpose of a malaria
propagule it's no different from the
purpose of a liver fluke or a maple tree
it's all one purpose to have this
marvelous machinery set to such a
uninteresting objective an uninteresting
objective that in the human context
results in all kinds of horror the worst
atrocities that humans are engaged in
our evolutionary in their nature for us
to be wired for that objective is an
appalling waste of our potential we
could and in fact I believe we must
commandeer our own machinery and take it
away from evolutions purpose and apply
to it a purpose that makes sense for
example we could architect mindful I'm
speaking as somebody who thinks
utopianism as the worst idea humans ever
had but we could architect a world in
which we had an abundant steady state in
which people's needs were met and they
were free to engage in the production of
meaning and beauty it would not be a
landscape perfectly free of competition
in fact competition would be at the
heart of such a landscape but the
competition would be towards something
that actually produced benefits for
people as a regular consequence should
we be doing that rather than figuring
out which people are unable to defend
them
and making up excuses to displace them
from the earth I think we should but
whether others will recognize in the
elucidation of our evolutionary purpose
this obligation that remains to be seen
and how does that repurposing all that
broader perspective relate to the
disagreement with Richard Dawkins on
stage Dawkins
expressed extreme reluctance about
applying evolutionary theory to human
beings he was very uncomfortable with
the idea of analyzing genocide warfare
really history in an evolutionary
context this shocked me Dawkins is the
iconic evolutionary thinker I would have
said fearless but to see him actually
frightened that we would apply this
logic in that context really made me
think now I do not share all of his
trepidations I share some of them I know
that bad Darwinism results in atrocities
but good Darwinism would be the cure for
those atrocities recognizing that you
are programmed for things that you the
conscious entity do not believe you
should be involved in leaves open the
possibility of controlling those
impulses seeing them coming is a far
better protection than pretending they
aren't there so I'm not arguing that it
is safe Dawkins is right that it is
dangerous but it is not as dangerous as
leaving these things unexplored if we're
going to move forward in history the way
we're going to do it is by understanding
the deeper lessons and learning to
protect ourselves from the patterns that
otherwise re-emerge and catch us by
surprise
I just want to pick up on something that
Brett said at the end there which really
reminds me of Jordan Peterson's concept
of the shadow the bread is saying if
we're not aware that we have
programs we're not aware that we're
monstrous then we are doomed to play
that out very similar to what Petersen
says about the shadow if we don't
realize that we're monsters then we're
much more likely to act that out in the
world and that also connects with
something that Brett said a few times
which is that Altru Maps must align
which I find really really interesting
like the kind of Jungian psychology of
Peterson which is an archetypal
mythological system can align with the
evolutionary biology in the way that
Brett's framing there so next up Brett
may have another public debate coming up
with another biologist called David
Sloan Wilson
if Twitter is anything to go by and he
and I recorded another short film about
that trying to contextualize and explain
why that's important which you can see
if you go to Brett's YouTube channel now
I put the link below this video here's a
quick clip of that there's an awful lot
riding on the question of whether or not
evolution takes place at the level of
the group this is dogged evolutionary
biology since Darwin so we also recorded
another few pieces including Brett's
take on the Jordan Peterson sam Harris
debates which is also really fascinating
we'll be trying to get that up in the
next few days and we've got a load more
interesting content coming up that we're
trying to find time to edit we've got in
McGilchrist we've got Heather hi in
we've got stanislav grof and quite a few
more and we're going to put that up on
the main channel and we're also going to
put on some patreon exclusive pieces as
well so if you want to see all of that
and to get access to a load more content
please do support us on patreon
and seriously
[Music]
you